Finding Aid for the Kenneth Macgowan Papers LSC.0887
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Manuscripts
  - Articles
    - --- Articles on motion pictures and television written at various times during Mr. Macgowan's life. v.p., v.d.; 21 items. Typescript (some carbon). The articles are alphabetically arranged by title within the folder. (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - The evolution of the American film: from Edison to the wide screen. n.p., n.d.; 9 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - The films and their future. Boston, Massachusetts, 8 leaves. Typescript, with corrections. (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Is Hollywood growing up? n.p., n.d.; 11 leaves. Typescript (carbon). Not known if published. (Box 13, Folder 6)
        (Another copy is filed in Box 21, folder 6)
      - [Hollywood's answer to TV of not TV, that is the question.] n.p., 1955.; 10 leaves. Typescript with corrections. (Box 13, Folder 6)
        Included are 3 versions, and 1 leaf of correspondence, plus 4 copies of article memos about the article.
      - The movies as an experiment in democracy. Mt. Vernon, New York, 6 leaves. Typescript, with corrections. (Box 13, Folder 6)
        Not known if published. Perhaps this was used in a newspaper column.
      - Movies: D.W. Griffith - still with us. Los Angeles, n.d.; 5 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - The movies: foreign and domestic at their best. Los Angeles, 1949.; 5 leaves. Typescript, with many corrections. Published in Script, March 1949. (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - The movies: the question of comedy. Los Angeles, 1948.; 8 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 6)
        Included are 2 copies, plus 1 printed copy.
        This article was published in Script, 1949.
      - On the screen. New York, n.d.; 17 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - [The paradox of Hollywood is that the first boom in the history of the talkies has brought unemployment...] Los Angeles, n.d.; 5 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 6)
        Noted at the top is N. Rep. Possibly this was published in The New Republic.
      - [To worrying mother:...] n.p., n.d.; 4 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - --- The film director's contribution to the screen. n.p., 1951.; 10 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 7)
      Also included are 5 printed copies.
      The article was published in The English Journal, vol.40 no.3, March 1951.
    - --- Articles on various aspects of the theater, written at different time during Mr. Macgowan's life. v.p., v.d.; 12 items. Typescript (some carbon). The articles are alphabetically arranged by title within the folder. (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Architecture for the audience. n.p., 1950 (?).; 17 leaves. Typescript and carbon. (Box 13, Folder 8)
        Included are 2 versions, 1 version with extensive corrections. Apparently this was delivered at a Michigan Conference on architecture.
      - [The community theatre...] n.p., n.d.; 2 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 8)
        2 copies are included.
      - Critics - corrupt and corrupted. Mt. Vernon, New York, 22 leaves. Typescript and carbon, with corrections. (Box 13, Folder 8)
        Included are 3 versions.
      - Democratizing the theatre. Philadelphia, n.d.; 6 leaves. Typescript. (Box 13, Folder 8)
        This probably was written as an article for the Evening Ledger, Philadelphia, and published therein, but the date is not indicated.
      - The function of the playwright in the working theatre. n.p., n.d.; 29 leaves. Typescript. (Box 13, Folder 8)
        Apparently this was delivered at the Northwest Drama Conference, but no place or date is noted. It is indicated, however, that this article was recorded on 2 tapes, but no tape is included.
      - [Inventions in the theatre--inventions back stage] n.p., n.d.; 11 leaves. Typescript. (Box 13, Folder 8)
        This apparently was a talk delivered at some meeting, but no place or date is noted. It is indicated though, that Kenneth Macgowan, director of the Provincetown Players, is the speaker, thereby dating it in the 1920's.
      - The playhouse. n.p., n.d.; 6 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Sequel's to A doll's house; a social criticism. Asheville, North Carolina, n.d.; 3 leaves. Typescript (carbon). Noted on the first leaf is sold to Harper's Weekly 3/12. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - --- Articles on various aspects of the theater... continued. v.p., v.d.; 12 items. Typescript (some carbon). All articles are filed alphabetically by title within the folder. (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Sex in the theater. New York City, New York, n.d.; 16 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - [Status of dramatic criticism in America...] Philadelphia (?), n.d.; 14 leaves. Typescript (carbon), with many corrections, and with additions. (Box 13, Folder 9)
        It is stated in the article that it is an address to the Drama League. Not known if published.
      - The theatre of beauty; Mr. Yeats talks on stage scenery. n.p., October 6, 1911.; 13 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 9)
        Included are 2 copies. This seems to be a class paper, report, or detailed notes.
      - The theatrical business. Philadelphia, n.d.; 11 leaves. Typescript. (Box 13, Folder 9)
        This was probably published in the Evening Ledger, Philadelphia, but no date is indicated.
      - [Untitled article about the director, actor, and theater as a whole] n.p., 28 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - [Untitled, incomplete article about New York theater] Brewster, New York, n.d.; 12 leaves. Typescript. (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - [Untitled article concerning theatrical trusts] Philadelphia, 1915.; 5 leaves. Typescript (carbon), with corrections. Noted on the first leaf is Sent to New Rep. 4/12/15. Not known if published, however. (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - [Untitled poem about the theater] n.p., n.d.; 1 leaf. Typescript with inked corrections and notes. Not noted if published. (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - --- Book reviews. v.p., v.d.; 11 items. Typescript (some carbon), and 1 printed copy of a review. (Box 13, Folder 10)
      Included also, is some correspondence re reviews.
      Items are alphabetically filed as follows:
      - Review of The Architecture of the Southwest, by Trent E. Sanford. Los Angeles, n.d.; 8 leaves. Typescript (mostly carbon). (Box 13, Folder 10)
        Included are 2 copies, plus 2 extra copies of the first page.
      - Review of A History of Modern Drama, edited by Barrett H. Clark and George Freedlay. Los Angeles, 2 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Review of Medieval American Art by Pat Keleman. Los Angeles, 1944.; 5 leaves. Typescript. (Box 13, Folder 10)
        Included are 2 versions, and 2 leaves of correspondence concerning the review. Probably published in Art News, ca. March 1944.
      - Review of Pioneering A People's Theatre, edited by Archibald Henderson. n.p., 1946.; 2 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 10)
        Included is 1 leaf of correspondence concerning the review. Published in the New York Herald-Tribune, 1947. The printed copy is also included.
      - Review entitled The Theatre of Democracy, about The Theatre of To-day by H.K. Moderwell. n.p., n.d.; 4 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - --- Review of Report on Blacklisting by John Cogley. n.p., 1956.; 7 items. Typescript (some carbon) and printed material. (Box 13, Folder 11)
      Included are 3 versions of the review, 1 carbon copy of a letter from Kenneth Macgowan to John Cogley, various notes, and a printed copy of the review.
  - Manuscripts and Notes
    - Art and economics in the American theatre. New York, Approximately 150 leaves. Typescript. (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Included is a synopsis of the work. The above title is apparently a tentative one, for a list of alternative titles is given.
    - --- Art and economics in the American theatre; another copy. New York, Approximately 150 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - --- The Leonardo of our theatre. Los Angeles, 1960.; 6 items. Typescript (some carbon) and printed material. (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Included are 4 letters concerning the article, a typescript carbon copy of the article, and 1 printed copy of the article.
      This is an article about Norman Bel Geddes, and was published in Theatre Arts, January 1961.
    - --- The stage goes stagestruck, (or the stagestruck stage). New York, n.d.; 9 leaves. Typescript with many corrections. (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - --- [Untitled article about theater in Greece, perhaps to be part of a book] n.p., 1954.; 23 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 14, Folder 5)
      Plus 1 leaf of correspondence concerning the article.
    - --- Encyclopedia article about American theater. Los Angeles, 1953.; 56 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Included are 3 letters concerning the article.
      This is an article that was written for the Encyclopedia Dello Spettacolo, Rome, Italy.
    - --- The theatre of today and tomorrow. New York, 1929.; 27 leaves. Typescript, plus 1 leaf of related correspondence. (Box 14, Folder 7)
      Apparently this is a typescript of a lecture that was sent to Theatre Arts Monthly for possible publication. It was not published by them, however, and it is not indicated if and where it was published.
    - --- Miscellaneous articles submitted to the Consolidated Press Association for publication. New York, 1923.; 21 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 14, Folder 8)
      Plus 1 leaf of correspondence concerning the material.
    - --- Theatre in the round. Los Angeles, 1948.; 4 items. Typescript (carbon). (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Included are 3 typescript copies of the article, plus 1 printed copy, clipped from a newspaper.
    - --- Eulogy for Dudley Nichols. n.p., n.d.; 12 leaves. Typescript (carbon). 4 copies are included. (Box 14, Folder 10)
      On one of the copies the following note appears, I think this was read at Services for Dudley Nichols, EM. (Edna Macgowan)
    - --- Ideas and outlines for literary works, with notes and details. New York, 21 leaves. Holograph and typescript. (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - --- Miscellaneous leaves of manuscript and fragments of manuscript. n.p., 14 leaves. Typescript (much carbon). Filed in no particular order. (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - --- Miscellaneous leaves of manuscript and fragments of manuscript, continued. n.p., 29 leaves. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). Filed in no particular order. (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - --- Miscellaneous leaves of manuscript and fragments and notes re various speeches and lectures given by Kenneth Macgowan. v.p., v.d.; Approximately 45 leaves and notes. Typescript (mostly carbon), and 1 photocopy. Filed in no particular order. (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - --- Miscellaneous notes and fragments of material, primarily about theater. v.p., v.d.; Approximately 35 items. Holograph and typescript. Filed in no particular (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Material re Books by Kenneth Macgowan
    - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re The Living Stage, written by Kenneth Macgowan and William Melnitz. v.p., 1954-1959.; 30 items. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). Filed alphabetically, H - Z. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Brandt, Dorothy., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Campbell, Lily B., 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Cheney Sheldon., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Craig, Edward., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Faulkner, Seldon., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Freedley, George., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Hartnoll, Phyllis., 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Hewitt, Barney., 3 items. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Hodges, C. Walter., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Kinne, Wisner Payne., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Larson, Orville K., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Mielziner, Jo., 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Morgan, Dan., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Potenze, Jaime., 3 items. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Sevin, Nureddin., 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Southern, Richard., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Sprague, Arthur Polly., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Weaver, Robert C., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified letters, and some carbon copies of letters from Kenneth Macgowan to various persons re The Living Stage. v.p., v.d.; 5 items. Typescript (mostly carbon). (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and Prentice-Hall Incorporated, re The Living Stage. v.p., 1955-1961.; 37 items. Typescript (some carbon). Also included are various ephemeral items. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Outline, typescript (carbon), and sample printed pages for The Living Stage. n.p., 7 items. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Notes, comments, corrections, and various fragments of material re The Living Stage. n.p., Approximately 10 items. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals about The Living Stage, plus reviews and clippings probably used in research and for revisions of the work. v.p., 1953-1959.; 13 items. Filed in no particular order. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Advertising material for The Living Stage. v.p., v.d.; 54 items. (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Included are various cards, mailers, brochures, etc.
    - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons, plus numerous notes, re Patterns in Playwriting. v.p., 1949-1961.; Approximately 31 items. Typescript (few carbon). (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons, plus notes and ephemera, re A Primer of Playwriting. v.p., 1948-1961.; Approximately 100 items. Typescript (much carbon). (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Anchor books. New York., 3 items. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Chapman, Robert., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Doubleday and Company, Incorporated, New York., 5 items. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Joseph, Nannine., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Random House, Incorporated, New York., 30 items. (Box 15, Folder 8)
        Includes correspondence from Saxe Commins, and Bennett Cerf.
      - Seldon, Samuel., 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Soedijomo, Luthfy., 4 items. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Carbon copies of letters from Kenneth Macgowan to various persons re A Primer of Playwriting, with no replies included. Los Angeles (?), v.d.; 6 items. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - A group of miscellaneous notes, and inserts, and royalty statements, v.p., v.d.; Approximately 55 items. Typescript (much carbon), and some printed and photocopy. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, primarily between Kenneth Macgowan and Prentice-Hall, Incorporated, re Yesterday, Today and Tomorrow. v.p., 1954-1959.; 27 items. Typescript (some carbon). (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence re Sleuths, Edited by Kenneth Macgowan
    Also, miscellaneous notes and fragments of manuscript material.
    - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re Sleuths, an anthology of detective stories edited by Kenneth Macgowan. v.p., 1930-1932.; 96 items. Typescript (much carbon), and printed material. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      Also included are some newspaper clippings of reviews of Sleuths, and various other ephemera.
      The arrangement is alphabetical, according to author concerned, with all items re each author chronologically filed.
      Correspondents, and authors concerned, include, A - C:
      - Aubrey-Fletcher, Henry Lancelot, 1887-., 6 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
        Also included are 3 printed stories of C.I.D.... by Henry Wade, pseudonym of Mr. Aubrey-Fletcher.
      - Bailey, Henry Christopher, 1878-., 4 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
        Includes correspondence about him.
      - Barr, Robert, 1850-1912., 13 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
        Included is a short typescript (carbon) biography of Robert Barr.
      - Bentley, Edmund Clerihew, 1872-., 10 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Beresford, John Davies, 1873-1947., 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Burgess, Gelett, 1855-., 13 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Chesterton, Gilbert Keith, 1874-1936., 7 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Christie, Agatha (Miller) 1881-., 6 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Cohen, Octavus Roy, 1891-., 28 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Cole, George Douglas Howard, 1889-1959., 5 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re Sleuths.... continued. v.p., 1930-1961.; 96 items. Typescript (some carbon), plus a few ephemera. Arranged as in folder 1. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        Correspondents, and authors concerned, include, D - R:
        - Doyle, Sir Arthur Conan, 1859-1930., 8 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
          Mention is also made of G.K. Chesterton in one of the letters.
        - England, George Allan, 1877-1936., 3 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Freeman, Richard Austin, 1862-., 14 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Futrelle, Jacques, 1875-1912., 6 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Joseph, Nannine., 1 carbon copy of a letter from Kenneth Macgowan to his literary agent, Miss Joseph. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Kitchin, Frederick Harcourt, 1887-., 5 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Morrison, Arthur, 1863-., 18 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - O'Higgins, Harvey Jerrold, 1876-1927., 5 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Orczy, Emmuska, baroness, 1865-1948., 12 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
          Includes correspondence about her.
        - Phillpotts, Eden, 1862-1960., 7 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Reeve, Arthur S., 7 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        - Roberts, Carl Eric Bechhofer, 1894-., 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence... re Sleuths.... continued. v.p., 1930-1932.; 85 items. Typescript (some carbon). Arranged as in folders 1 and 2. (Box 16, Folder 3)
        Correspondents, and authors concerned, include, S - Z:
        - Sayers, Dorothy Leigh, 1893-1957., 17 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Smith, Ernest Bramah, d. 1942., 17 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Stribling, Thomas Sigismund, 1881-., 13 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Wallace, Edgar, 1875-1932., 15 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Webster, Frederick Annesley Michael, 1886-., 9 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
        - Wynne, Anthony., 4 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence re the stories of more than one author, for inclusion in Sleuths. v.p., 1930-1932.; 3 items. Typescript (some carbon). (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence re the work as a whole, consisting of letters to Kenneth Macgowan from Harcourt, Brace and Company, Incorporated, New York. New York, 1931-1932.; 6 items. Typescript. (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Unidentified correspondence, fragments, and notes re Sleuths. v.p., v.d.; 8 items. Holograph and typescript (some carbon). (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Untitled, incomplete mystery story. n.p., n.d.; 17 leaves. Typescript (few carbon leaves).
        Included also are 2 newspaper clippings, perhaps from which the idea for the story was taken.
      - Miscellaneous notes and fragments of manuscript material. n.p., Approximately 30 items. (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous notes and fragments of manuscript material. n.p., Approximately 60 items. (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous notes. n.p., n.d.; Approximately 60 items. (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous notes. n.p., n.d.; Approximately 50 items. (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous notes. n.p., n.d.; Approximately 75 items. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Behind the Screen: the History and Technique of the Motion Picture
    - Manuscript Material
      - Behind the screen; the history and technique of the motion picture. [Los Angeles, 1960-1963].; Approximately 1085 leaves. Typescript (mostly carbon). (Box 17, Folder 1 - 18 (Chapters 1-18), Folder 1 - 14 (Chapters 19-29, 33, 34))
        With some ephemera.
        Included are chapters 1-29, 33 and 34, with each chapter filed separately in a manilla folder in the 2 boxes. Box 17 contains chapters 1-19, and box 18, chapters 19-29, 33 and 34. There is a second typescript copy of chapters 33 and 34 in box 18.
        Many of the leaves are typescript, photocopies; many of the leaves are duplicates, and often, leaves are in no particular order within a folder. Several chapters are incomplete.
        Notes, and a few miscellaneous ephemera are included.
        The work was published in 1965 by the Delacorte Press. A review of the work, by Robert Kirsch, can be found in the collection in box 52, folder 3.
    - Miscellaneous Material
      - Behind the screen: the history and technique of the motion picture. [Los Angeles], Approximately 500 leaves. Typescript (mostly carbon). (Box 19, Folder 1-8)
        Miscellaneous leaves of manuscript, many paste-up sheets, plus notes and fragments.
        The leaves are not arranged in any particular order within the folder.
    - Miscellaneous Leaves of Manuscript, Notes and Research Material
      - Miscellaneous leaves of manuscript about the development of the wide screen, used in Behind the screen: the history and technique of the motion picture. n.p., Approximately 50 leaves. Typescript (carbon). (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Research material, primarily ephemera, about the development of the wide screen, used for Behind the screen.... v.p., v.d.; 20 items. Typescript and printed. (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals about the development of the wide screen, used as research material for Behind the screen.... v.p., v.d.; 18 items. (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous notes, lists, and other material re Behind the screen... n.p.,., The material consists of numerous loose, unordered sheets and fragments of information, mostly typescript, used in connection with the writing of the book. (Box 20, Folder 4 and 5)
      - Miscellaneous leaves of manuscript re an outline, and list of contents for Behind the screen.... v.p., v.d.; Approximately 50 items. (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals primarily about various aspects of the motion picture processes, etc., used as research material for Behind the screen.... v.p., v.d.; Approximately 50 items. (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals plus various other ephemera, primarily about various aspects of motion pictures, etc., used as research material for Behind the screen.... v.p., v.d.; Approximately 40 items. (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous ephemera used as research material for Behind the screen... v.p., v.d.; 4 items. (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Research material for Behind the screen.... v.p., v.d.; Approximately 25 items. (Box 20, Folder 10)
        Including clippings and miscellaneous ephemera re box office grosses.
      - Whole magazines and newspapers included in research material for Behind the screen.... v.p., v.d.; 9 items. (Box 20, Folder 11)
      - Miscellaneous lists of motion pictures, various notes, and other ephemera included in research material for Behind the screen.... v.p., v.d.; Approximately 40 items. (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and Ephemera
    - Correspondence between Kenneth Macgowan and various persons re Behind the screen.... v.p., 1935-1963.; Approximately 105 items. Holograph and typescript. Arranged alphabetically, A - H. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Actors' equity association. New York., 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Allen, John E., 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Association of motion picture producers. Hollywood, California., 2 items. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - The Atlantic Monthly Press. Boston, Massachusetts., 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Ball, Bob., 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Barclay, A., 1 item. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Barnes, John., 2 items. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Better theaters. New York., 5 items. (Box 21, Folder 1)